<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Text Type="AltaxoBase,Altaxo.Text.TextDocument,0">
  <Name>09_Appendix\00_FitFunctions\Retardation\Modulus\HavriliakNegamiModulusBaseFunction</Name>
  <CreationTime>2021-07-13T12:35:54.1404372+02:00</CreationTime>
  <LastChangeTime>2021-07-13T12:35:54.1404372+02:00</LastChangeTime>
  <Notes />
  <Properties Type="AltaxoBase,Altaxo.Main.Properties.PropertyBag,0">
    <Properties Count="0" AssemblyVersion="4.8.3257.0" />
  </Properties>
  <StyleName />
  <SourceText>The underlying base function models the generalized complex dynamic modulus in dependence on the circular frequency $\omega=2 \pi f$ as:

$$
M'(\omega) + i M''(\omega) = \left [\frac{1}{M_{\infty}} + \left ( \frac{1}{M_{0}}-\frac{1}{M_{\infty}} \right ) \frac{1}{(1+(i \tau \omega)^{\alpha})^{\gamma}} + Flowterm \right ]^{-1} \\
Flowterm = \cases{
-\frac{i \sigma}{\omega} \thickspace\thickspace\mathrm{for} \thickspace \mathrm{InvertViscosity=true} \cr -\frac{i}{\omega\eta} \thickspace\thickspace\mathrm{for} \thickspace \mathrm{InvertViscosity=false}}
$$

with the circular frequency $\omega$ being the independent variable (or, depending on an option, the frequency $f$, $\omega=2\pi f$), and $M'$ and $M''$ being the dependent variables, namely the real and imaginary part of the complex dynamic modulus $M^*$.

The typical use case is a fit to the complex dynamic mechanical modulus (e.g. shear modulus $G^*$ or Young's modulus $Y^*$).

The parameters are:

- $M_{\infty}$ : high frequency modulus limit
- $M_0$ : low frequency modulus limit
- $\tau$ : retardation time (attention: this is not the same as the relaxation time, e.g. the maximum of $M''$ is considerably shifted with respect to $ 1/\tau $ !)
- $\alpha$, $\gamma$ : shape exponents (usually $ 0&lt;\alpha\le 1 $ and $ 0&lt;\gamma\le 1 $)
- $\sigma$ : generalized fluidity (inverse viscosity)
- $\eta$ : generalized viscosity


The available options are:

- `UseFrequencyInsteadOfOmega`:  
If true, the frequency $f$ is used as the independent variable, thus $\omega$ in the formula above is replaced by $ 2\pi f $.   
If false, the circular frequency $\omega$ is used as the independent variable.

- `UseFlowTerm`:  
If true, the flow term in above formula is used.   
If false, the flow term is not used, and the parameter corresponding with the flow term will not show in the fit.

- `InvertViscosity`:  
If true, the parameter in the flow term is an inverted viscosity (i.e.  fluidity). Thus the flow term generally is $-{i \sigma}/{\omega}$.  
If false, the parameter in the flow term is a viscosity, and the flow term generally is $-{i}/{(\omega\eta)}$.

- `LogarithmizeResult`:  
If true, the resulting values of $M'$ and $M''$ are logarithmized (decadic logarithm).  
If false, the original values are used.

&gt; Note:  
&gt; Since in most cases $M_{\infty}$ and $M_0$ differ by several orders of magnitude, your fit function will also cover several orders of magnitude. This will result in a poor fit of the low modulus data. To avoid this behavior, you should either use a NaturalLogarithmTransformation for both your data and for the fit function's dependent variables, or use the option in this fit function to logarithmize the results and then use a DecadicLogarithmTransformation to transform your data.  
</SourceText>
  <IsHyphenationEnabled />
  <Images Count="0" />
</Text>