<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Text Type="AltaxoBase,Altaxo.Text.TextDocument,0">
  <Name>09_Appendix\01_CommandLine\_Text</Name>
  <CreationTime>2018-10-19T23:01:59.2034702+02:00</CreationTime>
  <LastChangeTime>2018-10-19T23:01:59.2034702+02:00</LastChangeTime>
  <Notes />
  <Properties Type="AltaxoBase,Altaxo.Main.Properties.PropertyBag,0">
    <Properties Count="0" AssemblyVersion="4.8.2881.0" />
  </Properties>
  <StyleName />
  <SourceText>### Altaxo's command line arguments

Altaxo can be started using either `AltaxoStartup.exe` or `AltaxoStartup32.exe`, located in the `bin` subfolder of the Altaxo installation folder.
`AltaxoStartup32.exe` starts Altaxo always in 32 bit mode. If using `AltaxoStartup.exe`, the mode Altaxo is started with depends on your system architecture (32 bit on 32-bit Windows systems, 64 bit on 64-bit Windows systems).

The following command line arguments can be used to start up Altaxo (both with `AltaxoStartup.exe` and `AltaxoStartup32.exe`:

- `xyz.axoprj` :  
	loads the Altaxo project named `xyz.axoprj`. This argument works both with Altaxo project files, and with Altaxo project folders.

- `-nologo` :   
	suppresses the show up of the Altaxo logo during startup.
	
- `-noExceptionBox` :  
	suppresses the show up of the exception box should an exception occur during startup or running of the application
	
- `-embedding` :  
	runs Altaxo in COM local server mode (do not use this unless you know exactly what you do). This command is used internally when you embed a graph object in another application, for instance in Microsoft Word or Powerpoint.

- `-executetablescript nameOfTheTable` :  
	executes the table script of the table `nameOfTheTable`. This argument can be used multiple times. The scripts are executed in the order they are given at the command line.
	
- `-noAutoUpdate`  :  
    Altaxo will not perform an auto update. Use this argument if you have more than one instance of Altaxo on your computer, and you want to keep that instance at a certain version, whereas the other instances should get updates.

- `-exit` :  
	if this argument is the last argument, Altaxo is exited before Altaxo's workbench is shown. All arguments before this argument are executed nevertheless (e.g. loading of a Altaxo project, executing a table script etc.). If this argument is not the last one, it is ignored.

</SourceText>
  <IsHyphenationEnabled />
  <Images Count="0" />
</Text>